Guide to the Ken Ratner Photographs circa 1992, 2013-2016 PR 373
New-York Historical Society
Ken Ratner photographs
circa 1992, 2013-2016
New-York Historical Society
Ratner, Ken, 1953-
PR 373
.1 Linear feet in one folder
The collection is comprised of 25 photographs by art collector and photographer Ken Ratner (1953-). All were taken in New York City, mostly in 2013-2016, and are black and white. Most emphasize light and shadow on buildings, streets, street corners, and pedestrians. Some are portraits.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in chronological order.
Biographical / Historical
Ken Ratner, an art collector and photographer, was born in New York City in 1953 and lived in Texas and California before returning to the city in the mid-1990s. From an early age, he began to draw focusing on portraits, but later street life and the urban poor would become his primary subject matter in both his drawing and photography. He took evening sketch classes at the Art Students League in New York City in the 1980s, and would regularly study artwork and photographs in museums, galleries, and art books.
Ratner is a self-taught photographer whose principal field of interest is the urban city, particularly its derelict aspects that one often shuns, ignores, fails to notice or avoids. Yet in these out of the way places, he discovers a rich humanity in keeping with his long-time interest in the work of the Ashcan School artists from the turn of the last century. Like many of those artists (John Sloan, Jerome Myers), Ratner is similarly inspired to go into the streets to seek out an inherent beauty in commonplace subjects. He aspires to incorporate into his photographs some of the keen observations that these artists recorded. Ratner also draws inspiration from the urban scenes of photographers Berenice Abbott, Walter Rosenblum and Helen Levitt.
"In photographing street scenes, black and white is my medium of choice. The medium allows for clearly defined and dramatic effects, and is well suited for emphasizing light and shadow. Balance is a critical aspect. One of the first things I do is to look at the four corners of a picture. It's vital to me that a picture be properly balanced. I concentrate on capturing scenes of the lower class and their environment. I find that these residents tend to reveal themselves in a more natural way than those living in affluent sections. Above all, it is my hope that people viewing my photographs will find them interesting and humanistic. I have tried to express this in my work."
(The above note was taken from a biographical note on the website of The Rockwell Museum in connection with an exhibition of Western Art from Ratner's collection.)
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers. Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ken Ratner, 2015-2016.
Scope and Contents
The collection is comprised of 25 black and white photographs taken by photographer Ken Ratner. The photographs vary somewhat in size, but are in the area of 12 x 8 inches. All of the photographs were taken in New York City.
Most of the photographs capture the play of light and shadows on buildings, streets and steet corners. Pedestrians, either single or in small groups, appear in several photographs, sometimes casting shadows of their own on the city streets. Some of the photographs are portraits, including one of a resident in a homeless shelter, which Ratner referred to as one of his strongest in an email with the donation to N-YHS.
All the photographs were titled, dated and signed by Ratner on the back. All the titles are noted in the container list.
Buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; New York (N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Black-and-white photographs.; Portrait photography -- New York (State) -- New York.
- Relic of the Lower East Side, circa 1992 (Box SC, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Photograph of elderly man, presumably Jewish, walking past a tailor's shop near Ludlow Street.
- Homeless Man Keeping Warm under Queensboro Bridge, circa 1992 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- Sweeping [Snow], Lower East Side, circa 1992 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- New Utrecht Avenue, Borough Park, 2013 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- Shadows on Broadway, 2013 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- Manhattan Bridge, #1, 2013 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- 125th Street (IRT Broadway-7th Avenue Line) Train Station, Harlem, 2013 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- Tribute to Derek Jeter in his Final Yankees Season, 34th Street & 7th Avenue, New York, 2014 (Box SC, Folder 1)
  Features billboard with image of Jeter with back to viewer; the word "respect" rendered as "re2pect" incorporating play on Jeter's uniform number.
- Shadows on Lexington, #1, 2014 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- Central Park Drummers, Late Afternoon Shadows, 2014 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- Chinatown Cook, 2014 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- Shapes and Shadows, New York, 2015 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- Window Cleaner over 45th Street, New York, 2015 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- Window Cleaners Through Glass Reflection, 45th Street, New York, 2015 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- Crown Building at Night, 2015 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- Guggenheim Museum, #1, 2015 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- Warren Building, 20th Street and Broadway, New York City, 2015 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- Chrysler Building [Reflection] in a Puddle, 2015 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- Fire Escapes, 17th Street, New York, 2015 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- View of the East River Looking North from 63rd Street, 2015 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- Jefferson Market [Reflection] in a Puddle, 2016 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- Sunlight and Shadow, East 56th Street and Lexington Avenue, 2016 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- Aerial Bridge over West 32nd Street, 2016 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- The Sherry-Netherland Building in Shadow, 5th Avenue, 2016 (Box SC, Folder 1)
- Homeless Shelter Resident, Alphabet City, 2016 (Box SC, Folder 1)